Let's learn about selection sort algorithm deeply and then move to implement its code in C language
and Java selection Sort is a sorting algorithm that selects the smallest element from unsorted list
in each iteration, and the place is that element at the beginning of the unsorted list.
The selection sort algorithm sought an array by repeatedly finding the minimum element considering ascending
order from unsorted part and putting it at the beginning.
So the algorithm maintains do sub arrays in a given array, the summary, which is already sorted,
and the remaining sub array which is on sorted.
Consider the example array.
We have six, 64, 25, 12, 22 and 11.
The first thing that we need is to find the minimum element in the array from zero to four and from
the index zero two and export because we have five elements and place it at the beginning.
So we have find that the minimum which is 11 and replace it at the minimum.
Have the first, OK?
The second way finding them minimum element in array.
But here we need to go through the index from one to four, not from zero to four, because we have
already sorted 11, we have find them minimum and now we are going to go through one.
And from the first and the there are index number one to the index number four.
So 11 is not included in this game.
Now we have index one, two, three and four.
OK.
We need to get that a minimum between them minimum is 12.
So we place it at the beginning of the essay from index one to four.
So we swap it with not the 12.
We swap it with twenty fi.
So now 11, 12, 25, 22 and 64, the third sink or the third step that we need to make is to find the
minimum element in array from index.
Now we considered that index zero and one is fully and fully fully sorted.
Now we need to sort the others one to do three and four.
We start from two till four and place it at the beginning of that to for what what is the minimum value
is 22, so we place it at the beginning of index two to four.
Which is replacing 25 and 25 goes to the placing of 22.
Now we considered that all of these three elements have been considered fully sorted.
Now we need to find the last step at the minimum between the Element three and four.
From Index three and four.
So this is three and this is four from index at three.
Retail Index four.
And place it at the beginning of three and four.
So what is the minimum, which is twenty five at this place, the already placed in the same position
and now we have our array is fully sorted.
This is the selection sort finding and selecting the minimum and every iteration and placing it at the
beginning of the array.
Let's see the algorithm in terms of coding.
This is the selection thought algorithm that we are going to make it in C language and write it in C
language in the next video and later on, we will make it an exercise and write it in Java language
and later exercises.
And later, so the selection sort array and size, the array and size.
30 meters or we can make the size.
We can't get the size outpacing the perimeter as you want.
So we're repeat until.
Size minus one times we repeat this size minus one times.
So said the first answer that element as the minimum.
This is the set of the first unsorted element as minimum.
We move the minimum at the beginning of the first.
Position for each of the unsorted element, this is the for each element, for each loop, which check
if the element less than the current minimum, we set the element as the new minimum.
This is every time that we need to find the minimum and we move it to the first position by swapping
the minimum, the first unsorted position.
This is the algorithm, if you are asked, right, that let's move to that complexity.
Time complexity of this selection sort is of and square, because every time we need to go through all
the elements and we loop through the elements and we test every time we move that iteration to another
new element, we move it by looping through nested loops.
So the nested loops will give us a time complexity or the square in this election sort auxiliary space
space complexities of what the good thing about the selection, sort it is.
It never makes more than all of and swaps and can be useful when memory right is a costly operation.
OK, so this is a good algorithm.
If you have a shortage in memory or because there is no auxiliary space needed and we need to make a
selection sort more, not more than often because every time we select the minimum, we know the minimum
and we move it.
That left out and that outer left most.
OK.
This is this election, so let's move and implement it in the sea language and learn about the.